ILGWU. Jay Mazur papers, 5780/203
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU. Jay Mazur papers, 1951-1995
bulk 1983-1995.
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. President's Office;
5780/203
39 cubic feet
38 linear feet
Records
Consists of the records of Jay Mazur, during his term as President of the ILGWU until its merger with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers of America to form the Union of Needletrades, Industrial, and Textile Employees (UNITE) in 1995. Included in Mazur's files are alphabetical subject files which contain correspondence, memoranda, notes, testimonies, news clippings, and other printed material on persons, organizations, and topics relating to the work of the ILGWU. Also, these papers include correspondence files, as well as records documenting Mazur's work on the AFL-CIO Executive Council and the ILGWU's General Executive Board.
6791862
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff
Date completed:
June 2011
EAD encoding:
Cheryl Beredo, June 2011
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was founded in New York City in 1900 by mostly Socialist immigrant workers who sought to unite the various crafts in the growing women's garment industry. The union soon reflected changes in the sector and rapidly organized thousands of unskilled and semi-skilled women, mostly Jewish and Italian young immigrants. Exemplifying the "new unionism," the ILGWU led two of the most widespread and best-known industrial strikes of the early Twentieth Century: the shirtwaist makers' strike of 1909 in New York City and the cloak makers' strike of 1910 in Chicago. The union also tried to adapt to the fragmented and unstable nature of the industry. It adopted the "protocol of peace," a system of industrial relations that attempted to ensure stability and limit strikes and production disruption by providing for an arbitration system to resolve disputes.
The ILGWU exemplified the European-style social unionism of its founding members. They pursued bread and butter issues but provided educational opportunities, benefits, and social programs to union members as well. In 1919, the ILGWU became the first American union to negotiate an unemployment compensation fund that was contributed to by its employers. The ILGWU also pioneered in the establishment of an extremely progressive health care program for its members which included not only regional Union Health Centers but also a resort for union workers, known as Unity House. The Union also had an imaginative and pioneering Education Department which not only trained workers in traditional union techniques, but provided courses in citizenship and the English language.
David Dubinsky, an immigrant from Belarus who came to the US in 1911, provided strong leadership that led to unprecedented growth in the union during his presidency from 1932 to 1966. He led the union through successful internal anti-communist struggles, built on the ascendancy of industrial unionism by encouraging the formation of the Committee for Industrial Organization, and helped the union become an important political force in New York City and state politics, and in the national Democratic Party and Liberal Party as well.
In the period following the Second World War, the union suffered a decline in membership as manufacturers avoided unionization and took advantage of less expensive labor by moving shops from the urban centers in the northeast to the south, and later abroad. The ethnic and racial character of the ILGWU also changed as European immigrants were supplanted by Asians, Latin Americans, African- Americans, and immigrants from the Caribbean.
In July 1995 the ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU) at a joint convention, forming UNITE (Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees). At the time the new union had a membership of about 250,000 in the United States, Canada, and Puerto Rico.
Biographical / Historical
Jay Mazur was born in New York City on May 21, 1932. A graduate of the ILGWU Training Institute, Mazur began working for the ILGWU at the age of 18, beginning with organizing and educational work with Local 22 in New York City. He was Director of Organization and Education for Local 40, then Director of Organization for Local 23, before becoming Assistant Manager of the newly merged Locals 23 and 25 in 1964. From 1977 to 1983, Mazur was Manager of Local 23-25, the Blouse, Skirt and Sportswear Workers' Union. Elected General Secretary-Treasurer of the ILGWU in 1983, Mazur served in that capacity until he succeeded Sol C. Chaikin as President of the ILGWU in 1986. He served as President of the ILGWU until 1995, when it merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers of America to form the Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE). From 1995 until his retirement in 2001, Mazur was president of UNITE. In addition to his work for the ILGWU and UNITE, Mazur served on the Executive Council of the AFL-CIO, as well as the Industrial Union Department of the AFL-CIO.
Scope and Contents
Consists of the records of Jay Mazur, during his term as President of the ILGWU until its merger with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers of America to form the Union of Needletrades, Industrial, and Textile Employees (UNITE) in 1995. Included in Mazur's files are alphabetical subject files which contain correspondence, memoranda, notes, testimonies, news clippings, and other printed material on persons, organizations, and topics relating to the work of the ILGWU. Also, these papers include correspondence files, as well as records documenting Mazur's work on the AFL-CIO Executive Council and the ILGWU's General Executive Board.
Conditions Governing Access
The ILGWU Records, except for publications and materials produced for publication, are restricted. Materials created prior to twenty years from the current date are open to researchers only with prior written permission from the Director of the Kheel Center; materials created during the past twenty-years are closed; the minutes of the General Executive Board are closed. For more information contact the Kheel Center.
Related Materials
5780. ILGWU records
5780/059. ILGWU. Local 23-25 records
5780/059 P. ILGWU. Local 23-25 photographs
5780/059 PUBS. ILGWU. Local 23-25 publications
5780/095. ILGWU. Local 23-25 records
5780/095 G. ILGWU. Local 23-25 graphics
5780/154. President's Office records
6000/010. UNITE. President's Office (Jay Mazur). Files
6000/010 AV. UNITE. President's Office Videotapes
General
"Permanent deposit"
Arrangement
Textile industry -- New York (State); Textile workers -- Labor unions -- New York (State); Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- New York (State); Clothing trade -- Labor unions -- New York (State); International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union; Mazur, Jay; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. President's Office.; Union of Needletrades, Industrial, and Textile Employees; Union of Needletrades, Industrial, and Textile Employees. President's Office; UNITE HERE (Organization)
6791862
- Series I. ILGWU
  - ILGWU History, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - UNITE, Constitution of a Merged Union, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes legal opinion allowing merger of ILGWU and ACTWU; memo to Mazur from ILGWU asst president Gus Tyler re preamble, December 9, 1994; earlier draft with marked-up edits reflecting meeting with ACTWU president Jack Sheinkman, December 7, 1994; related correspondence
  - ILGWU/ACTWU Merger Committee, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Memo to Mazur re meeting of Merger Committee, April 12, 1994; related documents
  - ILGWU (UNITE), merger, General Executive Board, Adam Klein Study, February 7, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Agenda for General Executive Board meeting, February 1993; topics for discussion at retreat; report on organizing activities, December 23, 1992; notes for February 7-8, 1993, GEB executive session; memo from Adam Klein re next steps of strategic review of ILGWU, October 30, 1991; Klein proposed work plan through June 1992; notes on Ross Perot; material from the Triangle Civic Association, Melville, NY
  - ILGWU (UNITE), merger, General Executive Board, Adam Klein Study, July 20, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Memo from Mazur re retreat to discuss strategic planning outlined in Klein study, April 10, 1992; personal and confidential memo to Mazur from exec asst James Parrott outlining issues for GEB executive session, January 20, 1992, with outline of remarks
  - ILGWU Convention, 1986 and 1989, 1986-1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Copy of Convention Daily for 39th Convention, May 30, 1986; letter of retirement from Henoch Mendelsund, director of ILGWU archives, March 20, 1986; "On the Move" publication at 1989 convention re staff; outline re AIM, Associate ILGWU Members (former and potential members), described at founding convention, December 14, 1988
  - ILGWU Convention, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Booklet, Signature of 450,000, pictorial history of ILGWU, for 65th Anniversary Convention, May 1965; report of the Health & Welfare Retirement and Supplementary Unemployment-Severance Funds, January 1, 1965 – December 31, 1965
  - ILGWU General Executive Board (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - ILGWU, General Advisory Council, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Minutes of GAC meeting of December 7 – 9, 1994, with attached analysis of Dunlop Commission recommendations, report, "Worker Rights and Trade: Democracy's Next Frontier"; meeting notice; memo to Mazur from Carl Proper recommending comments re Leslie Fay; talking points for Mazur re need to rebuild progressive base and revitalized agenda for defeated Democratic Party, Leslie Fay strike, merger with ACTWU
  - ILGWU General Advisory Council, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    See also Speeches – General Advisory Council 1993 Handwritten notes by Mazur, January 22, 1994; printed outline of notes for meeting, January 5, 1994; agenda for February 16, 1994, GAC meeting; agenda, summary of reports re health care from October 26-27, 1993, meeting, with cover letter to ILGWU vice presidents from Mazur, November 29, 1993; outline of remarks by Mazur for March 14 dinner re opportunities with Clinton administration, difficulty influencing trade policy; notecards for March 15, 1993, dinner remarks; agenda for GAC meeting of March 14-16, 1993
  - ILGWU General Advisory Council, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Outlines of Mazur remarks for November 13, 1990, GAC meeting, in memos from exec asst James Parrott; agenda of meeting; outline of remarks for September 24, 1991, meeting, focusing on health care; reports from workshops and committees at GAC meeting of September 25, 1991; minutes of November 11-14, 1990, GAC meeting re major market negotiations, with cover memo to General Executive Board from Mazur, calling meeting "most successful and productive this group has ever had"
  - ILGWU General Advisory Council, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Meeting agendas; memo re creation of General Advisory Council, with racial and gender composition in 1985 and 1986, January 1985; memo re purpose of establishing GAC in 1984 to expand participation by middle-level officers, January 30, 1987; list of members, 1986; letter to Mazur from Pacific Northwest District Council business agent Frank D. Monti, reminding him that he would like to be considered for Advisory Council, with attached resume, May 11, 1987; confidential memo to Mazur from Susan Cowell summarizing discussions at GAC meeting, June 15, 1987; handwritten notes by Mazur
  - ILGWU General Advisory Council, 1984-1994 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - ILGWU Major Market Negotiations, 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - ILGWU Major Market Negotiations, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    List of task forces with descriptions of duties and members; memo to Mazur and others re demands, September 12, 1990; draft report of benefit fund task force, January 2, 1991; preliminary report, task force on benefits, January 8, 1991; minutes of the task force on benefits, October 15, 1990; report of task force on contract language, January 10, 1991; letter to Mazur from American Cloak and Suit Manufacturers Association re dire conditions in industry, July 23, 1990; chronology for 1991 outerwear negotiations; minutes of communications task force meeting, December 3, 1990
  - ILGWU Major Market Negotiations, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    General Executive Board Executive Committee agenda, February 28, 1991; proposed two-tier liquidated damages for imports; policy guidelines; demands, outerwear negotiations, February 28; short list and full demands, March 7; talking points; National Association of Blouse Manufacturers Proposals for Modifications of the Collective Bargaining Agreement; memo to Mazur re coverage of called-up Reservists and National Guard, February 26; consumer price index, U.S. and NY area; press releases, "ILGWU Begins Negotiations with Outerwear Employers in Northeast," March 13, and "ILGWU, Sportswear Employers Agree on Contracts for 55,000 Workers in Northeast," May 30; newspaper clippings; handwritten notes by Mazur
  - ILGWU Major Market Negotiations, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Memo to Mazur from exec asst James Parrott re staff comments at New York Joint Board meeting, January 8, 1988; memo from Parrott re discussions of 35-hour week, January 15, 1988; fact sheet on trends in collective bargaining settlements; draft fact sheet for negotiations between ILGWU and the outerwear industry in the northeast, March 4, 1988; chronology of events in the history of ILGWU (1846-1988), March 3, 1988; standardized form for interim agreements in the event of an impasse, developed by ILGWU general counsel Max Zimny, May 4; model collective bargaining agreement, from Zimny, February 25; remarks by Edgar Romney for opening session of negotiations, March 9; benefit fund fact sheet and cost of living background information, March 1; report of the task force on vacations and holidays, February 1988; Q&A sheet; Local 102 demands for 1988 trucking division; agreement between New York Coat and Suit Association, Inc., and Infants' Children's & Girl's Sportswear Association, and New York Coat, Suit, Dress, Rainwear and Allied Workers' Union Local 89-22-1 (sometimes called the Joint Board) and locals in the New Jersey Region, New England Region, Eastern Pennsylvania Region, South Jersey Joint Board and New York State District workers covered by the agreement, June 1, 1988; packet of newspaper clippings on contract settlement, with cover memo to communications task force from Susan Cowell, July 15 and April 27, 1988; ILGWU press releases
  - ILGWU Major Market Negotiations, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Minutes of meeting of major market strike task force, May 18, 1988; agreement between Allied Underwear Association, Inc., and Intimate Apparel Workers' Union, ILGWU and Amalgamated Ladies' Garment Cutters' Union, Local 10, ILGWU, July 1, 1984 to June 30, 1987; agreement between Intimate Apparel Manufacturers Association and Intimate Apparel Workers' Union, Local 62-32, ILGWU and Amalgamated Ladies' Garment Cutters' Union, Local 10, ILGWU, July 1, 1984, to June 30, 1987; memo to Mazur from Northeast, Western Pennsylvania and Ohio Department director Sol Hoffman re benefits issues discussed at staff meeting, December 11, 1987; letter from Hoffman to executive director of Atlantic Apparel Contractors' Association asking for early start on negotiations, citing desperate mutual problems in the industry, December 14, 1987; terms of clothing settlement, 1987; letter to members of Local 23-25 from manager Edgar Romney, noting upcoming series of meetings to discuss what members want in next contract, December 1987
  - ILGWU Major Market Negotiations, Communications Task Force, 1987-1990 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Minutes of meeting January 15, 1988; outline of objectives; letters from Mazur to appointees, December 30, 1987; memo to Mazur from exec asst David Melman re preparations for 1991 major market negotiations, listing task forces, including communications, July 27, 1990
  - ILGWU Major Market Negotiations, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    see also Agreements – Greater Blouse 1985 Collective agreement, New York Skirt and Sportswear Association, 1982-1985; with the National Women's Neckwear and Scarf Association, June 1, 1982-May 31, 1985; demands of Local 91-105, March 18, 1985; agreement between Fashion Apparel Manufacturers Association and the Philadelphia Dress Joint Board; agreement with Associated Garment Industries (Underwear Branch) with the Missouri-Mississippi River Valley District Council and the Texas-Oklahoma District Council, 10/13/82 – 10/15/85; handwritten notes by Mazur
  - ILGWU Major Market Negotiations, Non-Accessible Allowances, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Memos to Mazur re New York Dress Joint Board
  - ILGWU Negotiations, Local 23-25, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Remarks by Edgar Romney, opening session, collective bargaining with New York Skirt and Sportswear Association and guests Greater Blouse, Skirt and Undergarment Association, April 2, 1985; proposals; memos re contract negotiation; translation of Chinatown press, week of March 4-11, 1985; handwritten notes
  - ILGWU Negotiations, New England Region, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    List of officers, handwritten notes; list of negotiation meeting dates
  - ILGWU Negotiations,Locals, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    See also Koret of North America 1985 Demands and proposals of Locals 23-25, 91-105, 132-98, Dressmakers' Joint Council, NY Skirt and Sportswear Association; memo to Mazur from Muzaffar Chishti re 1982 contract developments, April 30, 1985; financial records; newspaper clippings
  - ILGWU, Appointment Agendas, 1992-1994 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Daily reminder books for ILGWU president Jay Mazur
  - ILGWU, Mazur, New York City Managers Meetings, 1987-1989 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Talking points, outline of discussion; handwritten notes by exec asst James Parrott
  - ILGWU, Mazur, Regional Staff Meetings, 1987-1991 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Opening remarks for AFL-CIO Industrial Union Department (IUD) Legislative Conference March 20, 1991; suggestions by exec asst James Parrott for Pennsylvania staff meeting, December 5, 1990; suggestions for Atlanta staff meeting, July 22, 1989; outline of talking points Southeast staff conference, June 6, 1991; handwritten notes by Parrott, November 11, 1987
  - ILGWU, Mazur Staff, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Memo re staff changes in president's office, n.d.; resume of Mazur secretary Rema Sherwood, 1995
  - ILGWU, census comparison, 1986-1990 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Six-month comparisons of ILWGU membership figures by region/district/local, and percent change
  - ILGWU, staff payroll records, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Computer printout of names, annual salaries, local affiliations, week ending 12/31/91
  - ILGWU, Health and Safety Department, 1986-1988 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Minutes of Occupational Health and Safety Forum (also called Occupational Safety and Health Forum) Meeting, June 7, 1989, with list of attendees, mission statement, accounting statement; paper submitted to forum re drug abuse in the workplace by Chrysler Motors' director of Occupational Safety and Health Services, April 25, 1989; memo from ILGWU Health & Safety director Betty Plattus asking to distribute information on new OSHA formaldehyde standards to all regional managers; training contract with NYS Dept. of Labor and production agreement with Shop Talk Productions for educational videotape in English, Spanish, and Chinese re fire hazards and musculoskeletal hazards; materials related to mental health and stress in the workforce: "New Options for Reducing Blue-Collar Stress," by Arthur B. Shostak, professor of psychology, Drexel University, May 1984; brochure, participant list, bibliography for conference, "Workers and Their Mental Health: Strategic Planning for the Next Decade," Columbia University School of Social Work, April 1986; press releases from U.S. Dept. of Labor re OSHA; memo to Mazur from Plattus re affiliation with Union Health Center, October 1, 1986
  - ILGWU, Health Services, 1981-1987 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    see also ILGWU Benefit Funds 1984-1988 ILGWU Health Services Plan Report to the Board of Trustees, meeting agenda, asset manager's report (for period ending October 31, 1987); minutes of Board of Trustees meeting for December 11, 1986, asset manager's report (ending September 30, 1986); agenda for Board of Trustees meeting, December 4, 1984, with director's report; director's report for November 1, 1983; minutes of Nov. 30, 1982 trustees meetings; auditor's reports/financial statements; resolutions by Local 188, re health and safety, equal opportunity for women within union, March 26, 1986; memos re availability of pharmacy services; report of presentations at meeting of Committee for National Health Insurance re statistics on uninsured and underinsured, February 10, 1986; memo re Vision Maintenance Plan, Feb. 3, 1986; Blue Cross Blue Shield of Greater New York description of Health Education Department Worksite Programs re blood pressure screening, CPR training, health workshops, referral services, available publications; AFL-CIO conference invitation re Negotiating for Improved Health Care, Mar. 11, 1986; ILGWU Health Service Plan descriptions; handwritten notes by Mazur
  - ILGWU, International Relations Department, 1990-1994 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    see also FITITVC; see also ITGLWF Letter from ILGWU International Relations Department director Michele Briones to counterpart in Italy re Cygne Designs and subsidiary T.wear S.r.l.; letters in Spanish from Mazur to counterpart in Chile inquiring about identity of buyer for worker-abusing Domsey Trading Company (Brooklyn, NY), August 8, 1990, and contribution to labor organization FITITVC, February 7, 1990
  - Economic Policy Council, meeting, March 27, 1986 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    Correspondence re panel meeting, "U.S. Policy toward the Newly Emerging Industrial Countries"; memo replying to request from Mazur by ILG researcher Herman Starobin, with attached paper, "Export-Led Economic Development for Third-World Countries," October/November 1985
  - Economic Policy Council, 1986 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    "Work and Family in the United States: A Policy Initiative," by the Economic Policy Council of UNA-USA, December 1985; memos re release of report, with newspaper clippings; detailed summaries of January 1986 meetings by ILG exec. asst. James Parrott; address by Mazur, "A Labor Perspective on U.S. Policy toward Newly Industrialized Countries," May 19, 1986; related draft
  - Economic Policy Institute, annual report, papers/articles, 1990-1995 (Box 11, Folder 3)